So we have two goals in the evening classes
one is to
again to teach the ACI
Courses, there are 36 courses,
33 if you don't count the review courses
We're hoping to do three
Courses a year to do them over again. I haven't taught them in 27 years
Okay, so I started them 27 years ago and we recorded them with my dog
barking in the house and
So we're trying to kind of do it over again
Probably there's things in the early recordings that you should listen to when you have time
because I had a ... you know, I was in the middle of the Geshe course at that point, I think
This time through will be more ... kind of a friendly
presentation of someone who's been teaching for 40 years and
talking to people who who want to be teachers, and I think you may ...
I may mix in a lot of advices on how to teach and ...
And new ideas I've had about the courses since I first wrote them, but I would say
reading them over recently to prepare for this course
They're good ...
they're good stuff, and they stand. I have never ...
to my memory, I've never had a correction from someone ... a substantial correction for the for the courses. They there are good
translations they are
the real thing.
None of it is my writing, a hundred percent of the courses except for one page,
Which is secret.
So, I think it's 6,000 pages of translation and it's all straight translation, none of it's
by me, so it's all the great classics of
ancient times and
I think it was the first time, and I think Jeff will appreciate it, that
we were able to put in the original language with the translation. So every paragraph has the original
sutras and scriptures in the six thousand pages. So if, you know, if anyone thinks something is wrong,
or mistaken, or if Geshela put a lot of his own ideas in it, you can actually check the
Tibetan or the Sanskrit and you can see
every single word
where it came from. So I think in that sense the courses are amazing
and ...
we're going to ... the kind of the ...
what we'll be doing in the evening is we'll go through the course material
ahh for each class. So there are ten classes in course one, and I'll go through the material for each class. You will do
the normal homeworks
for the ACI courses, so even if you've done them before, I don't care.
There was a punishment in the monastery for
young monks who snuck off across the corn fields. It's about a two hour walk
to the local town to see movies and ...
If you get caught
You have to hold an Indian movie poster up in the assembly for two hours. You can't put it down or you get
"massaged" ... and
and
then you have to do prostrations,
you have to do like a thousand prostrations to all the monks and
there was a big argument in the monastery that this was not a punishment. This was an honor and
So doing the homeworks again ...
is an honor and it will increase your understanding, so I don't care if you've done them before you're going to do them again.
All right?  And please turn your homeworks in on time.
Which leads me to another thing? I'm
27 years older than I was before ...
and
I'm too old to deal with bad behavior,
and people who don't turn in their assignments and you know?
I'm not a babysitter anymore. When I first did the courses I was a babysitter ... and
I I lost a lot of hair
by doing the babysitting and and I'm assuming you are all mature ...
you know, stable people that I want you to behave well while you're here and I expect you to, and I ...
Frankly, I'm too old to put up with any misbehavior.
It's usually three people who take half the staff's time and
I'm not going to ... we're not going to do it. Okay? If you don't want to do your homeworks on time, or
you can't get here on time, or you have some other personal problems, then go solve them ... come back to the next one. Okay?
And I'm just going to be a tough guy ... yeah right, okay ...
So I'm going to go through ... you've got two homeworks you're going be doing, one is the ACI
Course homework and then secondly, you'll be doing a separate homework for the teacher training
which will include tips about how to teach,
what's the purpose of the Asian Classics Institute. You know ... how did we come up with it? What's the structure, things like that
Okay? So you'll have two homeworks to do every day, and we left you a block of time, unlike the SCIM classes,
which you have to do at midnight ...
we gave you ... two hours I think. Tim am I right? Two hours in the afternoon to do your homeworks
Okay? So there's no excuse. I
wrote it in 20 minutes, so ...
you can do it in two hours. Okay?
So I'm going to go straight through the homework because I have a bad habit of forgetting to go through the homework, and
just talking about stories and ...
I'm going to make sure I go through the two homeworks with you. Okay? Probably in the  ...
well, I'll probably just mix it up, okay?
Teacher training stuff and ...
Nah, let's do the teacher training stuff first, and then I'll do the coursework. Okay? So here we go ...
General comments, and I'm going to be following your homework ...
so maybe your first homework question is ...
What is the mission of
The Asian classics Institute? What is ACI meant to do? What are we supposed to be doing?
Why are you becoming a teacher, and what's the purpose of the organization of ACI? Okay?
So, first of all
ACI's mission is to ...
we call it
accuracy,
relevancy ... accurate,
relevant, and
accessible okay? Those are three words I expect on your homework.
Accurate,
relevant, and
accessible. We want to bring the ancient wisdom of Buddhism ... 25 centuries, two-and-a-half thousand years,
to the modern world
in a way which is accurate,
relevant, and
accessible, Okay? So what do I mean by these three things? Accurate means the stuff is good stuff. I almost said a bad word.
It's good stuff. Okay? It's the real
Buddhism. It's all the ancient texts and
Jing [Sutras] and it it's really really translated correctly and
It's all there. The original is in the document. So,
there's even people who have spent part of their lives
hyper-texting, connecting the English to the Tibetan, just to make dictionaries. So there's there's been teams for the last 20 years
just connecting the words to ... and they've confirmed that all the words are there. Okay?
So ...
It's accurate. Okay? And when you pass it on ...
you're going to do it accurately!
Okay? And you're going to pass it down
correctly. The stuff is there, it's like a recipe for a cake. Okay?
Like it's a really tasty cake and ...
or Jasso gave me his Guadalajara enchilada brown sauce ...
what's those chilies called?
Poblano. Yeah, I use Anaheim's you use poblano. But uh ...
he has a recipe for a Mexican dish right? It's his mom's or something like that.
Like it was very kind of him to give it to me. It's highly secret and
I made them for Veronica and she loves them. So anyway ...
but you don't mess with the recipe. Okay? The recipe has worked
for 25 centuries
Okay? it has worked for
the world for 25 centuries, so don't mess with it and we believe, okay check this out ...
we believe
that the person who started the tradition
was omniscient. Omniscient is not like your mom who doesn't know exactly where you were keeping stuff in your room,
although she knew you very well.
Omniscient means,
they can see everything about you, about your life. They can read your mind.
They know every detail of your life.
The person who wrote the original materials is watching this class right now.
25 centuries ago. Okay? So don't think you're going to improve
on what they did. Okay? Don't think they left something out, or they didn't know that...
I don't know ... bubblegum was going to be popular.
They know everything okay?
So trust it. Okay? Don't mess with it. Alright? That's my first ...
thing.
It was an
Incredible amount of work to translate 6,000 pages. Don't mess it up! Okay?
If you want to teach ...
you know, what do you call it ...
psychic healing or something, do it on your own time. Okay? Do it ... don't do it in an ACI class.
You're free as an ACI teacher. We don't require that
you follow Buddhism. You don't have to be a Buddhist to teach ACI
Okay? And there are many people around the world,
you know, who are not Buddhist who come to ACI and especially DCI courses. I don't care
what you are.
99% of the people in the world follow what their parents did,
and that's fine, I had a guy in Ireland ...
you guys know him, Kevin Thornton from Galway, and he says "Geshela I like this stuff, you know
but my daughters getting married and is it okay
that she gets married in the Galway Cathedral and not in our basement with the 12-armed Avalokiteshvara." "Is this okay?"
"Cuz it's more comfortable for everyone."
You know? So yeah, whatever your parents did, whatever church, synagogue, mosque,
you went to as a kid ... make your parents happy, make your family comfortable.
Do the holidays, you know, I don't do Hanukkah. I do Christmas. I still like Christmas.
These are cultural things, you know, whatever you did ... Spring Festival, I don't know,
as a kid with your parents, keep peace in your family. Okay. I'm ... we're not trying to make you a fanatic. Okay?
We're trying to spread information
that can help everybody in the world, and it does not have to be connected to a religion. Okay?
And ... If you choose to be a Buddhist, or you want to become a nun like some
wonderful people here ...
that's fine, you know become a nun, teach ACI, that's fine. Okay?
But you don't have to. Okay? it's up to you, okay do whatever is legal in your country, that's fine.
Okay?
And you don't have to look like a guru, or a Lama, or a priest. We are not making gurus,
we are not making Lamas. We are not making priests,
we're just ...
offering information to people which will help them with their lives, and in ACI with their future lives, and
all their lives to come, and it will not help just
people who attend a business seminar, it will help the entire universe, and there's a time in your practice, in
your meditations, when you will meet the universe and
every being in the universe. If you play your cards right, they say in English, if you study well,
and you keep to the program, and you do your meditations and your practices,
you can personally meet every living being in this universe and
and get to know them and love them, okay? The human
mind has this capacity due to emptiness. Okay?
So ...
you know, think big! Okay? The purpose of ACI
is to help the whole world. It's not a Buddhist sect, or a small Buddhist ... thing. Okay? It's a
it's a way of acting, and thinking, and
practicing that can help anyone. So we're not forcing people to follow a certain religion or something like that. Okay,
it doesn't matter. What your parents had on your
altar at home, do that!
Okay? That's fine. Have a crucifix in your ... I have, you know, and that's fine, and I feel happy with it. Okay?
Keep the holidays of your own culture your own country. Okay? Add to the spice of life
this delicious ice cream called ACI.
Okay? And make your life more beautiful and whole okay?
And we're not here to convince people or make them join something or ... there's no leader.
Okay? There's a bald guy in the desert ...
you know ...
teaching you a little bit.
Later, it'll be somebody else. It'll be you guys. Okay? You'll be bald too, I'm telling you ... and that's how you know when you're wise.
So I told him his hair cut, it he's cut the sides, but for me it would work the other way ...
so ... me and John.
Okay? So I think one of the most important things I'd say about the ACI courses is ... have fun,
don't be a fanatic. Okay, don't be a fundamentalist, you know? Have fun. Life ...
is
incredibly short. Yesterday I was 25, I swear to God I was 25 yesterday,
I swear, and then boop and I'm 66 and I'm like, whoa what happened, you know?
Don't get too serious about your life. Okay, don't be like grumpy and you know ...
like this, you know? Life goes like that. You might as well have fun. ACI should be fun.
I don't want like people being ... what do you call it?
"You have to do it this way, or you're a bad person", you know? Come on!
We're all going to die might as well ... we're in a boat that's sinking in the middle of the Pacific. Let's play some music and
eat a lot ...
before it goes down. Okay?
Like have fun teaching ACI. Okay? Nobody likes a grumpy ACI teacher, or
stressed out. I was in the back of a ...
meditation class, I went to spy on one of our new teachers ... many years ago, they're not here anymore don't worry about it,.
and uh ...two ladies were sitting in front of me, and
I snuck in in the back, and I was sitting behind these two ladies and the teacher was like really nervous and
drinking tea like this ... and all upset and angry and uptight ...
you know? Like you got to do it like ... you know? And then
this one lady turned to the other lady and she said, uh ...
"What do you think?" "I
don't know, you know, I don't know what kind of
meditation she's teaching, but whatever it is I don't want to learn it!"
"Because I don't want to be like that." Okay? So, be happy,
have fun.
The minute you become a teacher, you're going to get extra trouble ...
because the demons don't like it. Okay? So, trust me ...
starting tonight ...
you're going to have more trouble, more problems, more difficult people are going to show up,
and just tell them, the demons to
@!#$ you! And have fun, okay?
Because what are you going do with your life? You know? You're going to be grumpy your whole life?
You're going to tell people what to do? Okay?
So keep ... but keep it accurate. Okay? Number one, accurate. Okay?  Number two ...
Relevant ... okay? Like, tie these
courses to people's real life
Okay? Never teach a class
without tying the ancient wisdom to people's real problems, real life. Okay?
Like, you're not teaching some ancient books ...
you're teaching people how to be happy. Okay? If you're a success ...
people will be happy. I got a photo from Jeffrey Tzuoo in Taiwan ... yesterday and uh
he went to DCI 2, which is?
How to find your talent or your passion in life.
He went to a group of 50 blind people and
taught them DCI 2 ... okay?
And then they all said, "I want to be this". "I want to be this". This one young lady stood up and said, "I
want to be a competitive Archer." Ancient archery, ancient Chinese archery, you
know? This is in Taiwan, right?
She wants to be an Archer. She's blind, you know? And he's like, "okay, let's do it!" "Let's plant the seeds." You know?
And he sent me a photo yesterday. She's in an archery competition now, and
she almost hit the middle, and they agreed that it was okay to put a bell in the middle of the target.
So she just listens for the bell, and she shoots at the bell, so don't wear bells to those competitions!
But it was so cool, and they have such fun,
you know? The group is just ... I met ... some of them came to my yoga class.
Me and Alex taught them,
uh ... from ah ... Colorado, it's a country north of here.
And ... it was so much fun, you know? And we just had fun. So look, you have problems, I have problems
Okay? We all have problems. As a teacher ...
You're going to multiply your problems. Okay?
And ... but just realize other people have worse problems, okay? We're not blind okay? And we don't have cancer, we're still walking and ...
We have a brain, and we can study these beautiful things. Okay? So, be a little happy, okay?
Okay, so ....
relevant to people's lives, second rule. What's the first rule again?
Accurate. Don't mess with the recipe right? It's not going to taste the same, and it won't work the same!
Okay? I call it ... selling
fire extinguishers ... that don't work!
And I can't think of anything more cynical, or mean ..
then to try to make extra money
by selling a fire extinguisher
that doesn't work, and you know it doesn't work. Okay? So, if you want to mess with this fire extinguisher
This fire extinguisher is called, ACI courses.
36 courses. Okay? It works!
You you get a fire, you push the button, the fire goes out.
If your husband's mean to you, or your boss is being his usual self ...
Any problem you have, you push this ACI course fire extinguisher, it will put out the fire. And the fire called ...
death.
Okay? It puts it out. But if you mess with it, and it doesn't work anymore ...
can you imagine people like, "oh my mom's dying, what do I do?" "Oh just shoot him with ACI 6."
"Yeah, well I changed it ... it doesn't work anymore." Okay, understand? It's big ... important stakes.
It's an important thing. Okay? It's like the only ...
recipe for AIDS,
to treat AIDS. Like the only formula in the world. Don't mess with it! Okay? You can save millions of lives ...
but don't say, "oh this, this needs a little ... I don't know ...
sugar in it." Yeah, okay, and then it doesn't work for the people who have AIDS. Okay? Alright.
So that's the mission. Oh ...
Did I say? What was the last one?
Accessible, okay? Don't ...
there's a big temptation for baby teachers, and baby yoga teachers,
to show off how much they know ... and do poses that nobody else in the room can do, and then you're not teaching anymore.
You're just showing off. You see?
Really, you want to think about the poses that are going to help ...
the people in the class, you know? They don't care if you can do a ...
some weird pose. They just want to be healthy. Okay? So,
make it accessible. You can use Sanskrit words,
Chinese words, Pali ...
you can show off sometimes. Okay? I allow it. I
maybe do it sometimes ...
But uh ...
It's not the point, okay? It ... we want the information to
be open to everybody. We want it .. it's ... ACI courses are open source, okay?
Anyone ...
can download an ACI course. They've been online for ...
19 years, 20 years, okay? And they're free and they're online, anyone can download them.
We lost count, after the second year, of the number of downloads. It was up to 150 thousand then ...
okay? Multiply that times ten ... or
more, I don't know.
Okay? So, we wanted people to use it. Okay? Don't be ...
stingy and
don't be weird, you know? Don't use weird words and things that people can't understand. Judge your audience,
stay with the level of your audience,
if it means you have to throw out your lesson plan for the day, do it! In two seconds
Okay? Stay with the level of your audience. Okay?
Make it accessible. Okay? If the audience wants
you to go deeper, like if they're from a certain country I know ...
then, then accessible means ... deeper. Go deeper, okay? But, watch your audience, stay with your audience,
and go deeper if you need, and always accessible, and interesting, and fun. Okay? If it's boring it's not accessible.
Okay? If it's dry it's not accessible. If you're not prepared
to teach the class
it's not accessible. Okay? And ..
By the way, people are like dogs. Okay? The dog you hear barking on the ACI 1 recordings,
okay, whose name was Pancho Via ...
Because he was from Mexico, he was a chihuahua ...
and a mean chihuahua!
But uh
you know, I had some students, i had ... I started ACI with six students.
Okay? They came to my kitchen and we sat around the kitchen and
John Stillwell, this weird guy, said "let's record everything", and I'm like "why, what's the point?"
Sorry ... ok here ...
Okay ...
Uh ...
And people would come in to go to class, you know? And I remember this one lady who didn't like dogs and ...
she opened the door, she stepped in, and he ran up and go ahhh chomp!
And bit her leg, and oh my god!
We had to go to the hospital, she was going to sue me. We'll talk about that kind of stuff later ...
and ...
The thing is, before she said anything and before she did anything,
the dog could tell she didn't like dogs.
They have some
ESP or something, dog
clairvoyance, okay? And
they can tell, and your students in ACI can tell if you're prepared or not
okay? You can't B.S., you can't fake it. Okay? They'll know in five minutes
whether you know your stuff or not, so just cover yourself.
Know your stuff, know your material, okay?
Don't think that students don't know. The students know everything about you. They know your bad habits, they know you didn't meditate yesterday.
They can smell it. Okay? So the safest thing is to be a good person and
don't have any secrets. You seen what I mean? Be prepared for your class. Okay, cool?
All right, and it takes preparation because this is real stuff. Okay? This is hard stuff and
It takes preparation, and you will be so much happier If you spend ... make time to spend a few hours to get ready,
okay, or your classes. Alright, so the mission is to present ...
by the way, this is a homework question!
The mission and ...
is to present this ancient wisdom
openly to the world
without any need for them to join anything, or become a certain sect or something. Okay? And ...
It's accurate, and it applies to their real life, and
they can ... it's accessible to everybody. It's meant to be accessible. Okay? And
the the ...
immediate goal. Okay, gu tsok chu shi - a famous concept in Buddhism.
What's the immediate goal? Is they learn the material. Okay? The immediate goal
for this week, is you guys learn the classic by Je Tsongkapa
called the Three Principal Paths. Right? Of Buddhism. Principal Teachings of Buddhism. Okay, that's the immediate goal, we call, what's it called?
Gupa, okay gupa?
Gusok chu shi.
Is the immediate goal. The next goal
...
is to make people's lives
happy. Happier. Okay? Make their life happier, life is hard,
everyone has to die. We all get sick. You lose, you're going to lose every person you ever met,
and you're going to lose everything you ever
collected on the way — money, houses, family. You're going to lose everything. Okay? So, the short term goal is to ...
give people some happiness. Okay? Make them happy.
Another goal of ACI, and especially DCI, is to change
the way the world works. Okay? Right now for example
economically,
politically,
the model is competition. I will sell more stuff than you,
Coca-Cola fights Pepsi Cola, Kěndéjī [KFC] fights
McDonald's. Who can make the most money? Okay? This is ... and a lot of this thinking comes from America, I'm sorry.
If I'm faster, stronger, harder, fight with the other guys, I can I can make more money.
I can be, I can get more things. Okay?
ACI teaches the opposite is true, and
thinking that you get more
by being faster, stronger, meaner
is a
very serious mistake that causes all the conflict in the world — personal conflict, company conflict,
international conflict, war — comes from this thinking that
If you fight for more you can get it. Okay? So, ACI's
mission, immediate mission — make people happier in their home life, in their work life.
Second mission: change the model of the world. Okay? If it's true that I will make more money
by helping others to make money,
if it's true that America will have more energy supplies if they supply more oil to China, for example ...
if that's true, then as an ACI teacher
you can change the model that the whole world is working by, and would that be cool?
You know? Would that be cool? That would be something cool. And my dream is that it's anonymous.
People don't remember the name of the guy who started ACI, and
they don't even remember that it was ACI who got the new model started, maybe ACI can go away by then.
It's just the model, and when kids want something their parents teach them to give it to someone else, and that
becomes the model of the whole world. So, the next goal, the second goal
of ACI, first goal — make people happy,
and give them some comfort in this difficult life. Okay? Second goal —
change the model of the world
In a quiet way, and maybe we never get credit and that's fine. That's the credit. Okay?
Third goal —
okay, don't be a frog in a well. There's ...
many many worlds that you have not seen. Okay? Don't don't think your little world is
the end of all things okay? I mean
a woman came from Asia,
China, to DM [Diamond Mountain] a
couple years ago, a couple years ago, and she went outside at night and saw the stars. Okay, she's from Shangha okay?
The stars never shine in Shanghai ...
rarely, and ...
and she looked up, you know? And she's like ... there were millions, billions of stars!
This is the best place to see stars, one of the best places in the world to see stars,
we're two hours from the nearest serious grocery store
okay? And ...
and she came in and she asked the director,  she said, "uh ...
are they going to be here tomorrow?" "Are those going to be here tomorrow?"
You know?
So, all you have to do to understand the
far goal of ACI, is to go out tonight and
look at the sky, if it's ...  by the way it's going to get hot now ...
starting tomorrow. So you're going to be complaining about the heat. So enjoy the the spring — Arizona spring is one day,
and it goes away, okay? Enjoy it because you're going to be complaining about the air conditioning tomorrow.
Bring warm clothes to class if you're from
countries that don't
grow up on an air conditioner like we do. Okay? so bring ... like Luca, you know bring a nice
heavy coat to ... don't get sick. Many people have gotten sick here from the air conditioner. Okay? Bring a scarf, head,
coat, okay? Because I keep the room cold, and you're going to learn to keep the room cold ...
because otherwise people fall asleep! If they're freezing they can't fall asleep. They get sick, but okay, that's after you leave, okay.
So ...
go out and look at the stars and that's where we're headed, you know, my next planet is Sirius star system.
Follow the two feet of Orion. It's the bright ...
blueish star ...
off to his left foot and ...
so don't think small okay? There's ...
just look up, don't think this is the only world, don't be ... come on!
You know? The world's a little bigger than that
okay, and
it's fully the intention and goal of ACI
to spread this on other planets,
okay? In other worlds.
There are many worlds in this room that you can't see. There are many kinds of beings in this room
you can't see okay? And we're not stopping with this world,
we're not stopping with changing the paradigm, the model of this world because there are other worlds that are suffering also. You will see them
in time. Right now you're not
so worried about it, you know? "Oh that's in another country, that's in Africa,
I don't need to worry about it Geshela." Yeah, but there's
other worlds that we have to take care of. Okay? So, the goal is kind of ...
is not less than ...
destroying death
in all worlds, okay? And you have the capacity to do that — each person in this room
has the capacity to do that. Okay? Don't think small
Okay, don't think small.
Your goal is bigger. Okay? Our goal is bigger. ACI's goal
is that ... and you one day you will see it. Okay? And you'll say, "oh Geshela was right for once."
Okay... I put a second question here, it says "what's not the mission of ACI?"
I don't know, you could say a lot of things. I don't want to be unfriendly, I don't want to be a cult,
I don't want to be a certain religion,
I don't want to be mean to people and say "you're not my religion", you know? I don't want us to be famous.
So far, we've been really good at ...
you know, combined ACI-DCI is the largest Buddhist-based organization in the world.
But we don't talk about it. Okay, I don't care. It doesn't matter.
You know?
It's not ... we're not here as teachers to get people's attention.
Now, every person in this room likes people's attention, including the one talking ...
but you got to deal with it, okay? And as a teacher you have to
... control yourself a little bit. Okay? We're not here to make gurus, Lamas,
Imams, priests, ministers
pastors, you
know? Kung fu masters ...
it's not the goal. Okay?
We're here as servants to share what we had the good fortune to learn from our teachers and
it's not about you or me. Okay? It's about helping people. Okay?
All right, so that's what we're not —
we're not here for a personality cult, and we're not here to make Geshe Michael king of the world ...
or anybody else. Okay? We're here to help people. Okay?
Alright, second question on your homework — what kinds of people teach the formal ACI courses? Who can teach ACI?
I think it's an important question to start with. Now ...
we have an esteemed group of professors for this course,
they are very very senior
As senior as me,
right JB? And ...
they are kick-ass practitioners,
JB has been meditating, I don't know, forty years, he ...
he and Connie, both finished three-year retreats.
Jigme has finished very long retreats,
they've been in "the business" for a long time. They're good at it. Okay? The teachers are very
good at it, and we have a plan to
develop the course with you —
to collaborate with you. It's something we stole from Stanley and Alison.
You know? Let the students design the course and I can relax and
eat ....
chili rellenos ...
more often, okay?
So, our dream is
that we work with you, and we work with each other. So the professors will be meeting
every lunchtime, after our yoga practice, which everyone's going to do.
Someone was telling me today how much their body hurts and why they can't do yoga,
And I'm like, duh!
But uh ... come and sit on the mat and do something, you know?
It's okay,
you don't have to do everything that everybody else does. Forget everybody else, do some stretching,
let the body get blood, you know? Be healthier. Okay? After yoga we will have an hour lunch
with the professors, but we want your feedback
how to make this a cool course, and how to teach it more effectively. Okay? You're the first experiment, you're the laboratory,
but we want the laboratory rats
to tell us what they like, what they don't like,
how they think we can improve the teacher training. So we're kind of keeping it fluid, what we realized already
is that you cannot teach a teacher
for a week and let them go.
That would be like training a heart surgeon
in a week and giving them a razor blade and saying,
"Go for it!" Okay?
So we kind of made a decision,
which is negotiable, okay? Because you're all helping us develop it, this course ...
we think, come to three courses and
then we talk about certifying you for the first one. Okay? Got it?
And you don't have to do them in order if you're from South Africa.
Welcome.
There's been an underground ACI group in South Africa for a hundred years,
we finally met after, I don't know, 20 years ...
but ... you know, you ... you can ... you're welcome
to help design the course, help us design the course, and I think
it's going to take three
courses
to really give you enough foundation
to give you a "razor blade" and to go say, "do heart operations." Okay? And they don't have to be in order.
Well, see if you're from South Africa
come come next year, and the year after. Now, the answer to the question Geshe-la try to talk about the questions, okay?
Is that anyone can teach ACI. Anyone!
The courses are free online. The materials are free online. We locked them. You can't change them. Hehe.
Unless you retype them or something, okay?
Anyone is welcome to teach what we call "living room courses". Okay? And ideally
less than 15 people ...
in a living room and
you came to one class at ACI,
you can, you're very welcome to share it with your friends. Okay, there's no
limits on the materials, you can use the materials, you can ... you're welcome to share with friends. I
expect you to teach at least one ACI
Course 1 class on the airplane on the way home to the person sitting next to you.
Okay? And that, you don't have to come to three
courses to have permission to do that. Okay, everyone in the world has permission to
sit down with their friends in their living room. I know the Guadalajara
skyscraper penthouse
karma.
They have this karma to have the most beautiful
floor in the city.
It was given to them for their classes with a swimming pool on it at the top of the building and
the bar they don't go to okay? And ...
so, you're welcome to sit in your living room and,
and teach friends, okay?
if your country
does not allow
religious teaching, even in a living room,
you're still welcome to take this training and we ask you to teach it outside of your country. Okay? If your country doesn't allow
these kinds of teaching in that country we require
that you go to another location if you want to teach.
Okay? And if I find out that people, who are in a country where it's not allowed, are
endangering themselves or other people, I will remove your certification. Okay? So, clear?
Alright. And it's possible, in English they say, "where there's a will, there's a way".
If you love people enough, you will find a way to do it legally and correctly.
Okay? And I don't want anyone getting in trouble. Alright? Okay.
So that's .. what kinds of people can teach ACI? The answer is ...
anybody — if you have a head, even without a head, if you can find a way to express yourself ...
Okay?
"Certified" teacher has to come to the training. Certified teacher, who's listed on the website as a certified teacher,
you ... we have to train you. Okay? You have to go through the training. Okay? How many classes you have to come?
How many course do you have to come to? How much can you do online?
You know? How much can you do by ...
touching your head with another teacher ...
ee have to decide this week. Maybe you can help us with suggestions. We have to make it possible
for people to get the training
from South Africa or whatever. We were, we are working on
finding ways to certify teachers
With a responsible mix of online and in-person. How that's going to happen is pretty much up to this group,
especially the professors, okay?
Mentors. So ...
to teach "officially", groups of over 15, outside of your living room,
including online,
if it's over 15 people you must be certified — and you will be on a list of
certified teachers, and and what courses you're certified for, if we do it that way,
will also be online. It will be on our website. Okay?
And
we'll talk more about that whole process. There's a lot of questions you probably have, and don't stress about it.
I can't cover everything the first night. I got to do the homework,
but it'll be a cool system. You will like it.
We want you to teach — we desperately want you to teach and you are very valuable. The people who came here
to learn to be a teacher — it took me 40 years to find you, and I'm proud of each one of you for coming and
I'm going to make you a good teacher. Okay? So, that's the goal. Don't worry about it,
but I'm going make you a good teacher.
Okay ...
So, certified teachers—groups of 15 or more, "official"
ACI teacher, you got to be certified, your name will be on a list.
"What if I've been teaching for 20 years Geshela, and you never told me I needed this stuff?"
We'll have a special deal that will work out for grandfathering the grandfathers and grandmothers.
"Grandfathering" as a verb in English means ...
special exception for people have been teaching for a long time already. Okay?
But still we're going to demand certain things
that you retrain yourself in certain things, okay?
Just to make sure the quality of the teaching is good.
Accurate, okay?
Accessible and ...
relevant. Nice! Okay ...
next homework question.
The 36 formal study courses of ACI are divided into two broad groups. What are these groups named, and
what is the primary emphasis of each of the two groups? So, we have 36 courses, okay?
Formal study courses.
There are some other courses called
"Practice modules",  like special meditations like Tonglen. There's a 50 page
essay, collected from the classics.
No Geshe Michael, all classics on Tonglen. 50 pages I think, ...
and that's a separate thing.
You can learn that, but the 36 main courses, okay?
Are divided into 18 and 18 — the first 18 names on your homework,
which always gets people's attention for a while, is
ACI Foundation Courses. The 18
ACI
Foundation Courses. Okay? That's half of
the formal study courses of ACI.
Okay? And I'm going to explain the structure of those 18 tonight. Okay? That's another homework question,
okay? But, so far you just got a name, right?
ACI
Foundation Courses, okay?
By the way, just ... you probably, most of you know, the last three: 16, 17, and 18 are
review of the first 15, okay?
Now, the second 18 courses are
Dimond Way
Courses. And the Sanskrit is Vajrayana. Okay?
Diamond Way Courses right, the goal ...
okay ...
traditionally if you study those first 18 courses, and you work hard,
you can become a Buddha and help all those stars we were talking about in about a billion years.
Standard
time period
for a normal Buddha. Okay? I mean, I can't even count the number — call it a billion. It's probably too small.
If you study Diamond Way —
properly, accurately, accessibly, and
relevantly—
You can shorten that time to this lifetime — to one lifetime. Okay? And that's an incredible deal!
You know? That's a good deal! Okay?
But, it takes a lot of training to do the second 18 courses and as teachers I
expect you
to never
teach a person the second eighteen courses without the ...
first eighteen courses. It's like giving a kid a loaded gun.
Okay? They will hurt themselves. Okay? So, I ...
Okay? And I've tried, I said "oh, this person is special."
"I'll tell you what, you finish 12 courses, I'll give you the Vajrayana."
They all failed! I think the failure rate for people who didn't finish
the first 18 courses is close to a hundred percent, and I'm talking big failures.
Okay? Hurt people, messed up people's lives, messed up their own lives, okay?
Not cool. Okay? So,
Vajrayana is fast. There's a there's a Sanskrit word for those courses
called Tantra. Okay? We're not going to use the word
because it has a bad reputation in the world,
even in India. Okay? The word Tantra
has bad reputation in the world, because of
misbehavior — bad behavior of
teachers who were practicing other kinds of Tantra. I was in
Indonesia, no sorry. Close. Argentina, and
we have somebody for Argentina, where are you? Yeah, a couple — so anyway I was
asked to go to Uruguay and teach in ... what it called, Punta Del Este?
To a soccer team,
and it was cool, you know? And I did it and it was fun. This is the Monte Carlo of South America, right? And
it was on the beach and everything, but they were so cool. We worked until two o'clock at night together, and
on the ... in the airport ...
Montevideo?
What's it called?
Uruguay.
Yeah ... in the airport I saw, there's a huge poster in the bookstore it said, "Tantra secrets, sex,
killing chickens", you know? And I was like ...
we can't use this word, you know? So, I encourage you not to use this word
okay? Especially as an ACI teacher, there's a traditional name of
the higher teachings — advanced teachings
called Vajrayana—Diamond Way, and I prefer to use it. Tim pointed out to me that there's a Buddhist group calling themselves Diamond Way nowadays,
but, and there's a group calling themselves Kadampa also. That's fine,
I'm not going to avoid an important word because someone's using it. Okay?
So, you know what it means. It means a method
to help the whole universe in your lifetime. Okay? And to be honest, you don't want to
go through the billion years
anyway!
Okay? It's too much trouble. You got to die. You got to get diarrhea I don't know how many times.
You know? Don't do it! Just
plan on doing the second 18 courses, they are called the Diamond Way Courses.
Sometimes I call them Advanced Courses, but I thought it was too wimpy. They're not advanced courses, they're ultimate courses.
Okay? Diamond Way Courses, AND in my opinion—which is modest. In my opinion,
because I wrote them, they are the best Vajrayana courses in history.
They include every major topic of Vajrayana for the first time in one course. I ... I was at
the two Vajrayana monasteries of Tibet, and
I was there the night they started the debate ground. I debated
all the students in the Vajrayana monastery, and kicked their butt frankly ...
And
they don't have a good course as we have. Okay, I don't care.
Okay, this is the best in the world. Okay? So cool. Super cool. You can do it. Okay?
Vajrayana. Eighteen courses, so you got the answer to the question, right?
It's pretty simple.
You're not going to put
"Tantra" courses, and you're not going to call them that because people will get the wrong idea. Even in India, that word is very very ...
It ... for all Indian people it's very uncomfortable to use the word tantra, because of people who misused it
okay? So, so stick to Diamond Way. I don't want to see "Advanced Courses" on your homework!
They're better than that!
Okay? Alright ...
You guys okay? I'm going to go ...
straight through. I'm older than you, I have to stand up the whole time. I'm teaching three hours in the morning,
I'll go like this maybe ...
but if you have a
pee-pee emergency,
you are very welcome to just slip out, rather than taking it a ten-minute break that turns into a half-hour break.
Okay? We don't have much time together,
so if you have a ...
I took my old lady to the ballet
this week in Phoenix.
Getting her out of her nursing home, getting her into the car, getting her into her wheelchair, we were the last people in
the auditorium and they were waiting for us.
And I worked hard to get in there on time,
and she sat down they started to lower the lights and she said very loudly,
"I need to pee!"
And i'm like ...
already all the ushers are angry at us, you know? And I'm like, "alright".
You know? I've put her in her wheelchair and they waited for 15 minutes, you know? A huge auditorium
they waited for her for ... why did I mention that? Oh
I'm not going to take a break. It's too slow. Okay? Alright? Two hours straight through, you okay with that? But seriously, it's not
disrespectful, it's not wrong.
It's wrong to hurt your body. Okay? In Buddhism. So, if you ... if something ... if you drank a couple
sodas before the class,
just go and don't ask me, and don't look desperate. Okay?
Just ...
Just go. Okay. Phil's showing you the way
Okay. Alright next topic.
In the very short run, my thinking when I started the ACI courses was to ...
share the Geshe course with, with modern people outside of Tibet, you see? And
I was very excited. I was finishing my
Geshe degree. I was about three years from from finishing, four years from finishing, and I was so turned on by the Geshe course.
It's so amazing. It's so so cool ...
By the way, dge ba bshes gnyen, Ge-she, is short for dge ba bshes gnyen.
The Sanskrit is kalyana mitra, and it means "spiritual friend". Okay? So, "Ge-she"
is "kalyana
mitra", and it's not on your homework don't worry about it, and ...
but uh ...
It means spiritual friend, and and that's what I want you to be. That's what we're trying to make you.
People's spiritual friend. Spiritual guide. Okay?
So, the Geshe course is amazing, and I thought, because people were asking me to teach Buddhism, and I was like,
you know, blank it, let's do the whole Geshe course, you know?
And they're like, "we don't have 25 years", and I said, "well,
do you have seven years?" And ...
so we tried to do three courses,
six years, every year.
So they could have digestion time, which is highly desirable.
And I said, "okay let's do the Geshe course."
So, I built the 18 Foundation Courses on the Geshe course, and the Geshe course
started roughly a thousand years ago. Okay? People started getting the name Geshe
about a thousand years ago, at that time
those great Tsongkhapa monasteries were still 400 years out,
but
masters who who studied the great classics—Asian classes, and
and became masters of them, were already called Geshes a thousand years ago.
Okay? In the Kadampa times, there's kadampa Geshe Dorje Senje, we are studying his work, and
Geshe Drolungpa, we are studying his work.
These are from a thousand years ago.
Okay? So, Geshe started—the name, the title, started a thousand years ago. It became formalized about 600 years ago. Okay?
But that course was so interesting and so cool, that I wanted to share it with
with modern people. Okay? And ...
i'm going to brag, which is very unusual for me, ...
that is the first time women were taught the Geshe course in history—women in Tibet were not allowed to learn to read or write.
Okay?
The name for women in Tibetan is "bume (bud-med)" which means no penis,
or "kyemen (skye dmen)" which means "lower rebirth". These are the two words
in the Tibetan language for females.
Women. And they were not allowed to study the Geshe course, and we broke this ...
tradition and we got a lot of heat for it, a lot! And a lot of criticism for it.
Recently, the people who criticized us just passed the first woman Geshe,
but we did it ten years before that—
twenty years!
We were a little bit ahead right? When was it?
Two years ago?
The first woman Geshe.
Yeah, I'm just saying it wasn't allowed.
Okay? And so we did it.
Yeah, so my dream was that modern people, and and people who weren't monks were never allowed to study the Geshe course.
So, it's the first time people who are not in a monastery, who are not monks or nuns, and
women, were allowed to study the Geshe course. Why? I have no idea. There's ...
4,600 texts from ancient India. 2 were written by women I think, it may be 3, I don't know. Okay? We're breaking this ...
we're breaking this tradition. It's a bad tradition. Okay? And
99% of those traditions are beautiful. That one's bad!
So we're breaking it. Okay? And my dream was that. Okay?
So the Geshe course is based on five great topics,
which I'm about to tell you because they're on your homework, and you're going to pay attention
because they're on your homework?
Okay.
No, you have to teach them.
I'm going to go ...
I've written a document in your manual,
which is going to be online to save paper, and also so I can keep adding stuff during the week.
I wrote a 25-page essay about the foundation of the Geshe course and the ACI 18 courses
okay? The Foundation Courses, so you can read that and
all of this information is there and that will be ... you'll be able to access that tonight? Right? Am I right Tim?
The manual as it stands?
Yeah, and parts of the manual aren't finished. You'll see. Hehe.
But, the essay about the 18 courses, the 25 pages, and it's beautiful because I added color ...
pictures of all the Lamas, all the Masters. Chandrakirti, Dharmakirti,
Guna Prapha, Asanga. Okay? I did a lot of work ...
So five great topics are covered in the Geshe course, roughly in order of
higher school because there's four great schools and
that's your last homework question. Okay? So,
five great topics,
covered in four great schools of
ancient India. We are not talking about what? The four ...
schools of Tibetan Buddhism, okay? We're not talking about that. Okay? There are four
traditional schools in Tibetan Buddhism for the last thousand years. We're not talking about that,
we're talking about Buddhism for two-and-a-half thousand years in ancient India, there were four great schools. Okay? And
on the homework question, you're going to have to give five names because? Oh sorry,
let's do the topics first. Five great topics. Okay, I'm not talking school,
I'm talking Geshe topics
Okay? And it's a little bit different. If you really want to be cute on your homework,
you can connect the five great topics to the four great schools, but I'm not even asking that. Okay? I want ... separate questions.
Okay? Here's the five great topics. Okay?
Should I do them in order? I'd better do it the way I did it. Let me see ...
Yeah, and by the way also in the ... I gave you the ... what do you call it?
I gave you the
the schedule of the Geshe  course in the monastery—the 25 years. Like how much time on this subject? How much time on this?
Okay? I put it in reading okay?
Mmm, this I want to do in order. Okay.
Okay, first of the five great topics, okay? Not
schools, okay? First of the five great topics of the Geshe course, is ... I'm going to say Abhidharma, okay?
The English name is Higher Knowledge, Abhi Dharma, Higher Knowledge.
Okay? The first great topic of the Geshe course,
not in order of how you take it, but in order of
school is Abhidharma—Higher Knowledge. Okay? I didn't ask for it on the homework, but maybe I should have
each ...
of the five great topics of the Geshe course has an associated
classic—
great book. Okay? So, I'm just going to throw those names at you. It's not on your homework,
You can get it off the manual, okay?
But, Stanley can probably tell me the first one ...
Abhidharmakosha by? Vasubhandhu. Okay? Vasubhandhu.
Correct spelling is in the manual, you'll see. Okay? Vasubhandhu lived 350
AD. Okay? I'm not doing dynasties: Tong Cháo, Ming Cháo.
I'm going to use Western dates, okay?
I think we're all going to be wearing Chinese collars before the end of my time, and
talking in dynasties, but right now it's Christian days. Okay? So, call it ...
350 AD. The dates for these guys are very very difficult. There's no Indian history books, so forget it.
Okay, I'm just giving you estimate. Okay? I didn't have time to figure it out. I could probably do better, but okay 350 AD.
The the book is called the Treasure House of Higher Knowledge. The Treasure House of
Higher Knowledge. Okay? Abhidharma
Kosha, okay Kosha. Full of Noors.
Okay? And, and still
accountants in India are called Kotaris. It still comes from kosha. Okay? And Stanley happens to be transiting
until 2042 is our schedule, right?
46? Oh ...
We might have to speed up, ah...
A very important commentary, but it will take 20 years to translate
okay? And I translated one of the most important commentaries. First 12 years of my
Geshe studies I translated it, the whole commentary. Okay? So, that's the first great. What's the topic?
After the Buddha died ...
for 700 years ...
Just after he died ...
some of his more advanced students, said to be arhats, there's a debate about it ...
collected together
collections of his topics, seven great collections of
his teachings and they called those literature Higher Knowledge.
Okay? So, that was collected together
by students after the Buddha and ...
they kind of messed up
some important points. Okay? But 90% of it is
extremely important as a foundation of all Buddhism. Okay? So, Abhidharma is important,
it does not contain the highest teachings on emptiness. Okay? And ...
for 700 years after the Buddha, this is what was taught. Okay? That's what reached Sri Lanka,
Thailand, Burma, okay? This tradition. Okay? Alright ...
What's the subject matter ... I describe it this way ...
Oh anyway ...
Just about every major idea that the Buddha taught, okay?
It's like an encyclopedia, and you're constantly referring back to it.
For example,
the Four Steps of DCI come from there,
the, the Four Laws of Karma come from there, the Four Flowers come from there, the Four
Steps of Confession come from there. It's an amazing resource. Okay? It's an encyclopedia. Okay?
Second great topic is called Vinaya—Vowed Morality.
Promising,
through a commitment, to keep to a moral code—an ethical code. Okay? And there are eight great
divisions and you will study it during the ACI courses, okay?
Vinaya, okay, Vinaya comes from a root that means "to tame a wild horse".
Okay? So, that's what we're doing. Allison's translating Tsongkapa's greatest work on it,
a summary, okay ...
The great book here,
for studying
commitments,
is called the Vinaya Sutra okay? And we can ... right after that you should say it's not a?
sutra, okay? Sutra
technically means, a teaching given directly by the Buddha, and but it can also mean a
short book, or a short classic. Some of them are 12,000 pages, but ...
like the Yoga Sutra, okay, 210 verses that's all. It's about
12 pages or something, okay? So,
the
the Vinaya Sutra is the book we use to study Vinaya in the monastery, but it's not a sutra—
It's just a short book. Okay? You can call it: A
Short Book on Vowed Morality. Okay? And
the author's name is Guna
Prabha. G U N A
P R A
B H A, and it's in your reading. It's in your manual, don't stress about writing things.
I'm not using visuals because ah, it's in your manual. Okay? I don't want you to waste your time looking at a screen.
Okay? I want you to listen to oral
lineage, okay?
Guna Prabha. About ...
550 AD, okay? Pretty late. 550 AD. Okay? Third great topic. In
Sanskrit, is Pramana. Say Pramana.
If you want to be really good, roll the N back, "pra ma nuh". [In an Indian accent] I would like a cup of tea if you don't mind.
Okay, a lot of Sanskrit is said with a
tongue [back]. Pramana. Okay? Pramana means ...
valid perception, correct perception. I have changed the name of the third topic to Clear Thinking.
Clear Thinking, and I'm very happy. Okay? It took me twenty seven years,
but I'm happy with it. I never did like "Buddhist
perception and epistemological theory", okay?
What it is, is clear thinking, okay?
And you have to be trained in how to think clearly, and it's an incredibly valuable tool for
all Buddhists. Okay? So, it's called Pramana—Clear Thinking okay?
How to think clearly? What are the rules for
thinking clearly? And then, by the way,
lots of information about how we perceive things.
For example, the crucial discussion of ...
DCI level 7
Chi jedrak. Chi jedrak.
Okay?
General and characteristics, what do you call it?
Quality and characteristic. Okay? Very deep.
This topic is called in
Buddhism: the key to emptiness.
It's extremely important. Okay? It's not some boring thing. I lost half my students
when I taught ACI 13. Thirteen is a bad luck number in the West,
I don't know, what's a bad luck number in China? Ba ba ba is good, right?
Four. Anyway, 13 is really bad luck in in Western countries because Jesus' 13th student killed ...
helped him get killed. So, 13 is a bad number. They don't have 13th floor on most buildings in America.
Why did I say that? Oh, course 13,
which was logic, I lost half my students that that that year.
Okay? And I'm going to teach you the flow by the way—why did I teach one course after another, and
you should know that by the time we finish this week. Okay? You're going to know the names of the 18 courses,
you're going to be able to tell me the main ideas in the 18 courses, and
you're going to tell me—which even Geshela didn't know, why did he teach this one next?
Okay? But I ....
What do you call it? Revision? I went back and figured out a flow.
Okay? Ahhh, alright.
The school here, by the way, is the Sutrist
School in Sanskrit. You don't need to know the Sanskrit. Sutrist school—followers of sutra.
Guess what? Okay, Mr. Know-it-all ...
Yeah, don't look around ...
Why is it called the Sutrist School? Why did they choose the name Sutrist for themselves?
So the first school is called like Abhidharma, okay? Or Vinaya. Oh, by the way,
Vinaya is just part of the Abhidarma school. Okay?
Same school. Okay? What's Sutrist?
Good!
Yeah, they say to the Abhidharma guys, "you're just reading
stuff that was put together by the students." "We want to read the Xīnjīng [Heart Sutra], or the Jīngāng Jīng [Diamond Cutter Sutra]".
"We want to go to the sutras, we want the Buddha's own word."
Okay? So, the second school, you can call them Logic School, or you can call them Sutrist
School, because they say, "we only want sutra, we only want what the Buddha actually said". Okay? And
then they ended up being very
interested in how do you think clearly, because that's a tool that every Buddhist needs. Why?
The important
stuff for getting out of suffering are things you cannot see with your eyes and ears.
You must develop your mental capacity. You must develop
your clear thinking to see things that cannot be seen by ... by the eyes and the ears.
You must learn to
develop this tool. Pramana. Okay? You must learn to develop your mind
to see things that you can't see with your eyes. Sometimes you can call it ...
"third eye", okay? So, the third eye is not some weird
Diamond Way thing ...
It's the ability
to see things that cannot, like emptiness, that cannot be seen with your eyes. Okay? You develop this muscle here.
Okay? Alright. Next ...
topic—Geshe topic. How many Geshe topics?
5. Good. How many schools?
4, but 5 if you?
Split the?
Fourth school into ... 2, okay? But, we didn't get there yet.
Okay? Okay, fourth major topic of the Geshe course, we're kind of going up schools,
is ...
It's called, the Perfection of Wisdom. It's called,
The Perfection of Wisdom. Okay? Prajna
Paramita, in Chinese?
Bōrě bōluómì duō.
Okay?
Prajna. Say Praj na?
Para mi ta.
And actually Russian is the closest modern language, I'm aware of, to Sanskrit. It's it's very precise,
close to Russian. So there, you would say znayu [знать] right? For, for "I know" Yeah, I know, "ya znayu".
It's much closer to the Sanskrit, and and in general Russian pronunciation is much closer to the Sanskrit. It's cool.
So anyway, now ...
Perfection of Wisdom has at least three major meanings that contradict each other,
so you better know which Perfection of Wisdom you're talking about. Okay? When you talk about
the Geshe topic—the fourth Geshe topic, which is named
Perfection of Wisdom, say, in Tibetan?
Parchin.
Parchin, just short name "Parchin", okay?
It's the study of the Lower Middle Way school.
Perfection of Wisdom in the Geshe course only means the study of
the lower half of
the Middle Way school, highest school, okay?
It's only that.
Why?
Because those early Middle Way works by Bhavaviveka,
Asanga,
these present
every major topic of Mahayana—every major topic of the Higher Way. Okay? So, super cool
Aright? It's
It's when you reach Prajna Paramita in the monastery—the fourth major topic, that you start the Greater Way.
Mahayana, okay? Don't call it Mahayana to your students, learn to use your
language: Russian, Spanish, whatever.
Don't
drown your students under Sanskrit.
Okay? Don't force them to learn the same thing with an older name,
you're just putting obstacles in their way. Okay? So,
Perfection of Wisdom, in the monastery course, in the Geshe course, it just means:
The study of the lower half of the Middle Way.
Okay? Why? Vast encyclopedia of all great ideas of Mahayana,
except for the perfect explanation of emptiness.
Okay, so it's pretty cool and frankly
It's half of the Geshe course. It's twelve years of the Geshe course. Okay? It must be important.
Okay? I forgot to give you the important book for the
Pramana—clear-thinking schools. Okay? It's by
Dharma Kirti, and don't mix up your Kirtis
okay? You know I went on Wiki to see the dates for Dharmakirti that they thought, and
the picture of the Lama under Dharmakirti in Wikipedia is Chandrakirti, and it says that under the picture
In Tibetan, so I wrote all my friends who do that kind of stuff. I said, "can you fix it?"
They stole the picture from me,
which is okay. I
got it in Russia,
but ... and it has the name under it and they put it under the wrong Kirti, so don't get your Kirtis mixed up. Okay?
Dharmakirti is the great logician. Okay? And we study his book called,
A Commentary on
Valid perception, or clear-thinking, okay? in that case, what's valid perception or clear-thinking mean?
It's the work of his teacher, Dignaga.
That's why it's a commentary. Okay? But I'm not telling you that, just put Dharmakirti. Okay? By the way, it's a tradition in Buddhism
never to speak of your teacher—
your personal Lama,
with their, we call their "naked name". Jenba, ming jenba. So we're not really supposed to say Dharmakirti, and in ACI
Courses we try to use the word Master, Chinese people have a very good custom, they always say "oh,
Michael Lǎoshī, Geshe Michael Lǎoshī.  They always say Lǎoshī.
I mean, if you taught them how to change a tire on a car they'll call you Lǎoshī.
It's very polite, and
it's a tradition in Buddhism. We say Master Dharmakirti, and I prefer that you do that.
You don't have to be a Buddhist to study ACI, and you don't have to be a Buddhist to teach ACI,
but you should be respectful of the lineage. You call it Master Dharmakirti. Okay? Dates for Master Dharmakirti,
650 AD.
Now, who wrote the big book for
fourth topic?
Well, actually it was Maitreya and
then his secretary got credit for it.
Asanga okay? And
what's the ... so the book is by
Maitreya/Asanga, you can answer it that way if you want.
Half-brother of Vasubhandhu, 350 AD okay?
Same mother, and
what's the book called?
Yeah good, Jewel of
Realizations, the jewel of
Realizations. In Sanskrit?
Abhisamaya
alankara. Abhisamayalankara. Okay, but you don't need to know that. Okay? Just put Jewel of Realizations.
Very very important, for example:
DE NAS SENG GE RNAM BSGYINGS PA'I,
,TING NGE 'DZIN LA SNYOMS ZHUGS NAS, ,RTEN CING 'BREL 'BYUNG LUGS MTHUN DANG, ,LUGS MI MTHUN LA RTOG PAR BYED,
We have to memorize, most of these books in the monastery, these five great books.
That's the whole source for two things:
Lion's Dance, and
and thousands of books on the on the Twelve Links, is two
two lines of Sanskrit.
Okay? It's a hot book.
Okay, twelve years of the Geshe course. Okay, fifth topic. I know you're getting tired, you're going to be worse in a couple of days,
so just enjoy.
Fifth topic? Come on!
Middle Way, okay? Now ...
oh, by the way, the other two meanings of Perfection of Wisdom, which is not what it means in the Geshe course is
The sixth perfection of a bodhisattva—the sixth activity of a bodhisattva,
the sixth
topic of training for all bodhisattvas is wisdom—Prajna Paramita, okay?
The other meaning of Prajna Parmamita is a huge
group of sutras where the Buddha taught emptiness, but sometimes through very long stories,
like the 8000-Verses, or the 20,000-Verses, or the 25,000-Verses, or the
100,000-Verses okay?
It's a huge section in the scriptures called, Perfection of Wisdom, so don't get confused
okay? As a Geshe topic it means?
The?
Lower half of the Middle Way, which is a big deal. Not dummies
okay? Okay, here's the important homework question:
Nah, I'll tell you later. Ahh okay. Yeah, I got your attention though. Hehe.
Alright, so this fourth topic, I'm sorry the fifth topic is Middle Way—
Middle Way also refers to the fourth topic right? They're the lower half of the Middle Way, so don't forget
when you're listing Geshe topics, or you go to the monastery and they ask you, "what are you guys studying nowadays?"
Use the right names—they are nicknames. There are misnomers. Okay? Middle Way means the study of?
The higher half of the Middle Way school, okay? It's the study of the higher half of the Middle Way school.
The big big big book,
which is not the main book studied, is Nagarjuna's
Wisdom, it's just called Wisdom. Ok? By Nagarjuna. 200 AD.
Does that date strike a ...
Strike a bell?
Ring a bell?
yaah,  it's when Buddhism came back to what it was
700 years, after 700 years of Stanley Chen's Abhidharma.
Okay? Then Nagarjuna came back and said, "hey you guys are missing emptiness, man!"
"You don't got it right!" You know? So, he came, we call him, his nickname is
second Buddha on this planet, second Buddha to walk on this planet. Okay? 200 AD. He wrote a book
Which is sometimes just called ...
It's called Wisdom, but sometimes it's called, just called the Middle Way. Okay? So, the most famous commentary on it is called?
Entering the Middle Way, meaning Nagarjuna's book. Okay? It doesn't mean the Middle Way as a school and that's by?
Master Chan ... "Master" Chandrakirti, okay?
Around, I think it's 650,  let me check what I wrote here ...
I can't find it, but yeah 650, okay?
Yeah 650, mmm you guys with, you okay? Can I just keep going?
Yeah? [Question]
Yeah, yeah because the nickname of the book Wisdom is
is Middle Way.
Okay? So, Entering the Middle Way is actually means,
"learning to read Nagarjuna".
Okay? And ...
so it doesn't mean entering middle way philosophy for example, although by ... although we are okay? Okay, good question.
So those are the five great books—we memorize most of them in the monastery
over the course of the Geshe, Geshe
course, okay? ...
I did all of the Abhisamayalankara, I did the first four chapters of the Abhidharmakosha, which was a ... I almost said bitch, uh ....
and, you know, I've done pieces of the other ones, okay...
But you need that to walk, you shouldn't walk on the debate ground if you don't have them in your head. Okay? Alright now ...
I'm going to present them by school.
So, now we go to another homework question.
The four schools, and it's actually the last homework question, and I'm actually timing this class not so bad except I didn't get to your
ACI course ....
But that's okay, I
promised Tim I wouldn't do this, but I'm doing it, okay...
You might have to do half the homework tonight,
you might have to do homeworks in halves,  but anyway, okay.
The four schools—the four great schools of ancient India. Okay, they overlap a little bit. We'll see. First great school called ...
Detailist.
Detailist. Okay? "ist" means a member of a group in English, you know, like ... I don't know ..
republicanist ...
anyway ...
Detailist, Buddhist for example, okay? So,
yeah, so Detailist. Anybody, okay human dictionary ... anybody want to tell me why, who's not the human dictionary?
Jasso. Why are they called Detailist?
Oh, not really, I mean it's a good guess, but there's a book called
Yeah, there's a book called the Detailed Explanation
which is what they follow—that's their main Abhidharma book—that's their book, okay?
Yeah, Detailist means Vaibhashika, but part of the title of the book is Vaibhasha.
Okay, so Detailist
just means, their people, the first school of the four great schools of India
is called: people who like to read the book the Detailed Explanation? Okay? And
it's one of the books of Abhidharma. Okay?
Vaibhashika, okay Vaibhashika. Alright. You don't need to know the spelling, it's in your ...
by the way, it's so nice to see so many people with jet lag and I don't have, because all year it's the opposite.
Second great school. Oh by the way, Abhidharma, now Geshe topic in the four schools.
What's in the first school? which Geshe topic?
Two. Great! Abhidharma and?
Vinaya, are in the first school—so don't get confused between schools and topics.
I'm trying to confuse you, but show me you're smarter than that.
Five topics, four schools, they over ... they go like this. Okay? So first topic?
Higher knowledge. Second topic? Vowed Morality, are both part of the first school—the lowest school, by the way.
I'm going up. Vaibhashika, Vaibhashika—Detailst.
Abhidharma and Vinaya. Okay? I
prefer you don't use foreign words in your class, you know?
You use them because you're used to them,
you know? Kōng xìng,
you know? But ...
but just try to remember the, the first class you walked into. I remember
the first class I walked into, and people were like, "well the Vaibhashika
approach to the Abhidharma is not exactly what Vasubhandu would say, but it's more on the question of alaya vijnyana ...", and I'm like ...
and
for them, it's very easy. They
They, they've been in it for ten years, but don't forget your students are not.
Don't confuse them with a lot of Sanskrit. Don't don't make them ...
Abhidharma sounds comfortable for you because you heard it from ten years. Okay? So, don't do that to them.
Call it Higher Knowledge. Okay? First school?
Detailist school.
Second school? We talked about it.
Sutrist.
Sutrist. Okay? They follow the sutras. "We don't want those huge summaries done by human beings,
after the Buddha died, we want the Heart Sutra, we want the Diamond Cutter, we want the real sutras—
we want what he said." Okay?
Sutrist, okay? You can call them Logic School,
sometimes we call them Logic School. Now we're going to call them?
Clear Thinking School. Okay? Clear Thinking School. Okay? That's their main thing, topic number?
Three. Okay? Topic number three.
Now, with the first two schools, and with the first three topics, we have finished the branch called?
The Lower Way.
The Lower Way, okay? Now, you should know something about "Lower Way".
In Tibetan, it's "tek men", "men" means lower. Women are called "kye men". Same word: lower being.
Okay? I hope they change the language. They probably could if they really wanted to you know? That's something the French would do.
They'd have the courage to say, "let's change this word, it's not nice."
So anyway ...
those are Lower Way.
Literally, Hina ... Hina Yana, Hinayana.
Okay? "Hina" means
"Inferior", "lower" okay? Hinayana. Okay? Now,
you visit Sri Lanka, you visit Thailand, you visit Burma, do NOT call it?
Hinayana. You
might go to jail.
In their country, it's Theravada—the True Way.
Theravada. Okay? So get ... if you want to be polite
in a Buddhist group from one of those countries, don't use the word Hinayana. It's like "lower birth",
it's like calling a woman a "lower birth". It's not polite. Okay? It's kind of not very sweet
okay? But, in our scriptures it's called
Lower Way, okay? It's the same word:
"lower", okay?
So, the first two schools are Hinayana, and how many [Geshe] topics are Hinayana?
Three, or Theravada if you're sitting with people from Sri Lanka and Burma okay?
Alright ...
Third school?
Mind-Only School. Okay? Mind-Only School. Where is it in the five Geshe topics? $50 question!
Don't get ... I mentioned money and two people get excited, whaaat?
$25 to get the question!
Okay, anyway, you're both wrong, I save my money. I mean you're both not exactly precise. Okay, now
when does a Geshe
study the Mind-Only School, okay?
Yeah, exactly! Okay? [ACI] Course number?
15—What the Buddha Really Meant. Okay? What the Buddha Really Meant? Okay? We studied it
for year ... months, in a certain city in China ...
Yes?
I'm about to ...
refer to that,
but hang with me. So, the main place in the Geshe course, thank you, when you study Mind-Only is ...
when you study a course,
a book, a Sutra called What the Buddha ... What I Really Meant. What I Really Meant. Okay? And,
as the guys in the
CS Pure Gold program can tell you ...
Buddha taught three great periods in his life ... forget the ACI course 1, I'm going to do it tomorrow.
Buddha taught three great courses in his life—three great periods of his teaching. First one?
Is, I call it the "list period", he made lists.
"Hey, there's four truths, there's twelve links, there's an eightfold Arya path, there's the four steps of confession,
there's the four steps of karma, there's the four laws of karma, there's a six ...", you know?
And everyone is like, zzz ...
Okay? it's the list period of his life. The first teaching for example, he ever taught
was the four truths. Okay? So, he's just making lists, ten non-virtues, he was organizing stuff for people. Okay? And ...
then in the middle part of his life, he got up on a mountain—vultures peak, and he said, "by the way
all those lists I gave you,
the stuff in those lists, it don't exist!"
"It's not real." "Every list I gave you—every piece of every list ...
was not real." "Haha!" Hehe.
It's like a joke, you know? "Hehe, I fooled you guys for 20 years", you know?
So, guess what happened?
People freak out.
People freaked out, you know? And people came to him—Paramarthasamudgata. A Bodhisattva, and he said, "listen,
you spent the whole first part of your teaching career giving us lists, and we believe them and we practice them."
"Then, we got to the second part of your teaching career, like diamond mountain or something ...
instead of New York, and then you said, by the way, that list I gave you in New York is all BS!"
"None of it exists, you know?" "And, we're ... we're like confused Mr. Buddha." "Like, what's the real one?"
"Which one was real?"
What are two famous sutras from the second period—the second turning of the wheel?
Yeah, the Diamond Cutter Sutra and the Heart Sutra, okay? Like, nothing exists, nothing's real, okay?
So naturally, some people are going to come and say, "what the F?!" "What are you talking about?"
You know? "Everything's not real", and he said, "look, you
didn't get it, you know, let me explain it a different way", and he taught three characteristics of the?
Mind-Only School, and then he taught the Mind-Only School okay?
Which the Middle Way School
understood to be ... Middle Way School, even
in the third part of his life, and that started an argument that lasts until now.
Okay?
When Buddha ... by the way, the third turning of the wheel is called "clarifications",
the second turning of the wheel is called "emptiness". The first turn the wheel is called "lists".
Okay? "Turning of the wheel" means?
Teaching period but?
Why, "turning wheel"? Why is that the symbol of Buddhism?
Yeah, you pass .. I'm turning the wheel right now, and then you're going to turn the wheel when you get certified ...
as a DCI teacher, or you're going to turn the wheel on the airplane unofficially—as a living room teaching ...
Okay?
So three ... the third period,
it's very interesting because the Mind-Only guys said, "oh
let's start a school called Mind-Only", and the Middle Way guys said, "come on
he just talked about the same thing he talked about before", okay?
Got it?
Anyway, you don't get to study that argument until after you finish Higher Middle Way. It's considered part of Higher Middle Way.
It's considered, in the Geshe course, it's considered part of Higher middle Way, but
as Steven pointed out correctly,
It comes up very importantly in the teachings on karma, and it came up in
the Abhisamayalankara, right? Very important subjects
about the Mind-Only School, so you can say the  Mind-Only School touches on the other schools in different places, but the main
foundation of the  Mind-Only School is the Middle Way School, okay?
They take off from their argument with the Middle Way School. Okay? Third school?
Which topic in the monastery, in the Geshe course?
We're g ... no, of the five ...
Yeah, we're going to throw it in the Highest Middle Way, because that's where you study "drang ne" [the Art of Interpretation].
Okay, that's where you study "drang ne" [the Art of Interpretation]. Okay? We don't have a separate course in middle ... in Mind-Only in the monastery.
Okay? Alright. Hmm ...
Fourth school? Middle Way, okay?
That Middle Way is not the same as?
The middle Way which is a topic of the Geshe course.
Okay, as a school, Middle Way is
the 4th and highest school. As a Geshe topic, it's the fifth topic. It's not the same thing.
Okay, why?
Yeah, as a school
Middle Way is number four and it includes two parts—and the lower part is the fourth Geshe topic, which is not called Middle Way.
Confusing? Yeah...
Which is also the name of Nagarjuna's book which started the whole problem.
Okay!
So, as a school
Middle Way is the fourth school and the highest. As a topic, it's the fifth topic. As a school,
It has two little schools in it—two groups. As a topic, it's always the higher of those two groups. Got it? [Question]
No higher, okay? Alright, now since it's on your homework, and we're almost done.
There's two schools in the ... in the middle ... two groups, okay? I asked you, for the rest of your life
to call them the groups of the Middle Way School. Okay. First one is called?
in English?
Independent group, the independent group. Okay, the independent group, they're called independent. Okay?
And they wrote the books for?
the Geshe topic number?
Four, which is not called Middle Way, which is called?
Perfection of Wisdom, okay? I'm sorry ...
I'm just trying ... if you show up in the monastery and say you're studying Middle Way, and you talk about the Lower Middle Way,
you're in trouble!
Okay? Got it?
Alright.
Now, what we learned in our translation classes in Sedona,
which you're always welcome to come to, there's a tuition fee to pay for the air conditioning and ...
you're always welcome to sign up,
and we cover the classics—we translated three thousand pages in the last two years.
No one has ever done that okay? It's an awesome course, you should ... you're welcome to come and sit in on it,
you have to pay the fee, I'm sorry.
...
And in that ... in that
course, we learned a cool reason why the lower school is called "Independent". Okay, ready?
It's cool. It's super sexy ... to me.
Buddha said,
"things don't grow from themselves,
things don't grow from other things things, Things don't grow from both, and things don't grow from nothing."
That's very famous. Okay?
A big guy [Master Bhāvaviveka] in the lower middle way school said Buddha left a word out.
He should have said,
things don't grow from themselves,
number two: and things don't grow from something else—
"from their own side"!
"Ultimately"!
He should have said that, because normally things do grow from other things—trees grow from seeds,
you know?
So this Lower Middle Way guy [Bhāvaviveka] said, you should have said ... he should have said "ultimately."
They don't go from other things—when you say don't grow from other things you confuse everybody because they do grow from other things.
You should just say, "they don't go from other things ...
ultimately". Then,
everybody will understand what you're talking about, because when you say "things don't go from other things", well, what about trees?
Okay, got it?
Now, one hundred dollars.
Why should that opinion ... except for Word, you get ten dollars.
Why should that opinion be called "independent"?
Yeah!
They think the word has its own power—independent power,
because if someone's going to misunderstand
"doesn't grow from something else," they're also going to misunderstand "ultimately" because both words are empty.
They don't have power from their own side—the power of the word comes from you. You make a movie that ... the last movie you saw ...
Netflix is coming from you. That's why they don't make money ... just
kidding.
Got it?
If you think it's going to be easier for someone if you say the word "ultimately"
then you must think that word has more power than the other word, but
words don't have any power—the power in words comes from you.
Got it?
You're probably the only people in the world who understand why that school is named what it is. Now ...
what's the name of the Higher Middle Way school? We're almost done.
Yeah, consequence. Consequence, okay? Consequence. Prasangika, why called "consequence"?
So, Word comes up to me and says, "Geshela I have an idea." I said, "what?"
"All fruits are orange." "I saw an orange, somebody had an orange, somebody had a tangerine, I got this idea—all fruits are orange." Okay?
Ready?
Then I say, "oh really?"
"Look at this banana, I guess it's orange!"
Okay? So, the Highest Middle Way School is called what they're called,
"consequence",
referring to the absurd
consequences of the other guy's statements. The crazy
Implications of the other party's ideas. Okay. Got it? If you think I should have used the word "ultimate",
then I also should have said "fish".
Right?
It's effective.
Has the real meaning. It always refers to things that go like this ... right? From its own side.
Right? Okay? You could never call fishing "looking for girls," right? Because it has its own meaning.
Got it? Okay? You're getting the deep explanations.
Okay, the Highest Middle Way school is called "consequence" or "result", you see?
Because if you believe a wrong idea about emptiness,
the result is you're going to say stupid things like, "all fruits are orange." Okay? Got it?
And the way we fight those people is ... we say we don't say, "look Word, all fruits are not orange, there's other fruits."
"There's red apples, there's
yellow bananas." That's not the chill system of the Highest Middle Way.
The chill system of the Highest Middle Way is to show ...
to put a banana and a stick in his face and say, "you want this orange fruit Word?"
You know? You don't say, "I disagree." You don't say, "not all fruits are orange." You don't say, "this ...
this fruit is yellow." You say, "oh Word, here's another orange fruit for you."
Okay? That's called
"ridiculous consequence of his own position." The Highest Middle Way School is called that. Now, we're out of time. Am I right?
We got three minutes?
Last question on your homework. I know I said that already. I was just trying to keep your attention.
Last question. Honest. Just like, "what I really meant."
Last question on your homework.
How do we divide the four ancient schools
into two groups? On
what basis do we say,
Hinayana and Mahayana
for example?
You can say motivation.
Okay, the the lower two schools are supposedly not interested in saving the universe, they only ...
the three goals I out laid out for ACI right? 1. Make people happy. 2.
Change the model of the world. 3. go to Sirius,
change the universe. Okay? They don't believe in number three.
They actually don't believe in number two much. Okay? They just want to be happy. Okay? That's the traditional way to explain the difference between
Mahayana and Hinayana, but if you read the Abhidharmakosha, they discuss bodhisattvas,
and they discuss saving the world and being enlightened.
Oh, I'm going to kiss you, but you got that beard!
Perfect! Yeah, it's perfect. Yeah, that's the second answer to the question. The question says I want two answers. Number  one:
Lower school, higher school. Lower school doesn't have bodhisattvas.
They don't want to save the universe. Higher schools—Mind-Only and Middle Way, they want to save the universe. Abhidharma ...
sorry, Sutrist and
Detailist, they don't want to save the universe. But they do and it's in their books, duh!
But that's a traditional answer. Okay?
Now, if you want to go deeper—
which as ACI teachers, I'm sure,
talk about it in terms of the six flavors of emptiness. The way you divide the schools ...
the way you divide the four schools, the way you divide Hinayana and Mahayana
Is all based on how good is their emptiness explanation.
Okay, how good is it? Alright?
Let's do it.
You won't be able to stay late later because you'll be too tired.
Okay, you want to? Let's do it quick.
Okay, we're going to talk about the six flavors the emptiness that are the true basis of the differences between the schools,
because you got to understand the differences between schools to understand the structure of the Geshe course,
which you have to understand if you're going to understand the structure of?
The ACI Foundation Courses. Got it?
Okay? I'm trying to make you a real ACI teacher who understands what the hell is ACI.
Okay? You got to know the schools. You got to know the ...
the topics, okay ready?
And you got to know the six flavors of emptiness to know why the first two schools are lower, and the second two schools are Higher
Way, Mahayana/Hinayana got it?
Someone give me the first flavor emptiness? Quick quick! We did it like ten times in your city.
Yeah!
Things are .. by the way, every time you teach the six flavors the emptiness start out the sentence with the same words:
things are empty of _____
Or things don't have ____
Okay? And the blank, fill in the blank ____ for the first flavor emptiness is: things don't have lasting forever.
Okay? Your husband's not going to be
yelling at you forever. He's got to sleep. He's got to eat. Okay? Take refuge, which is real refuge,
in the understanding that he has to change—he cannot yell all night ... most of the night? Yes.
But he's got to take a break.
Okay?
And that's the lowest form of emptiness. Your husband who is yelling at you ... by the way, right now we're being?
Relevant to real life.
Your husband can't yell forever. Take refuge in emptiness. Okay?
First flavor of emptiness: nothing lasts forever.
What's the famous example I always give in ...
when I discuss it?
Abraham Lincoln, the most compassionate president in American history,
had to kill more people than any American president. Well, that's a ...
Okay? But, and when he had his big meeting with the generals, he said "the only good thing about this war is
It won't last forever." Okay? So, that's a low low low refuge. It don't work too good.
Okay? I'll put up with my husband because uh ...
He'll go to bed sooner or later.
Okay? It's not a very effective emptiness. You know, it'd be nice if you could just
stop him from ever yelling, but if you don't know that higher emptiness,
take refuge in the lower emptiness, which is real Buddhist refuge.
You know, I'm going to wait, I'm not going to say anything, he can keep yelling. He's got to take a break sooner or later.
You know, he's got to go to pee pee like you guys.
Okay? Lowest form of emptiness. What school?
Yeah, lowest school, lowest school, Detailist School. Second kind of emptiness?
Yeah!
Okay, there's
okay, second kind of emptiness. You cannot control things in this life. Forget it.
Okay?
There will come a day when you can't raise your arm.
Okay, don't tell me you can control your husband, or your finances, or your country.
Okay? You can't control your finger!
Okay? In the end, in the hospital, someone will have to hand you the water.
Trust me. I've been there so many times in this life.
Okay? Someone will have to .. you won't be able to ... you don't have control. You can't control anything.
Take refuge in this lower emptiness. What do you do in the kitchen?
"Ah, look, what the heck
if he's going to yell, he's going to yell." "You know?" "I tried, I talked to him, I died I did everything, he's still yelling." "Well, I
can't, I can't control everything." Okay, just relax. Okay? Is it a solution?
No. Does it help?
Yes, that's lower school! That's the definition of lower school!
Is it a solution? No. Does it make you feel better? Yeah.
Which school?
Is it? Yeah, you're right. Second school mostly. Okay? Second school mostly.
You got to kind of say mostly. Okay, third flavor emptiness for zero dollars?
rangnyi rangnyi chepay tanye jukpay jukshi yinpa ranggi tsennyi kyi
druppe tongwa
Things are empty of being called what they're called, because that's what they have to be called.
Things are empty of their names. Okay? How did Shakespeare say it?
I'm sorry ...
It doesn't really matter you can mix three and four if you want, okay, Lucas right. I'll go your way, it's probably my way ...
We do it with our elbow, right?
Mind-Only School right? Here's a seed.
You yelled at your kids a week ago,
a week went by, the seed
matured.
Then you walked into the kitchen and the seed opened into?
You and your husband.
One seed
splits into subject and object. Don't tell me your husband's a bad man. You are a
bad person.
You created
the
yeller and the yellee?
You created the yeller and the person getting yelled at. Don't blame ...
don't blame him.
You created him. Who brought you in the kitchen?
Who brought him in the kitchen?
what are you talking ... why are you whining?
Why are you getting angry? If you don't like it, stop yelling at your kids.
Don't plant the tree if you don't like the branches. Got it?
What school? Are you sure? This is not a solution to the problems of the universe?
Stop making bad seed that split into husband and wife? Sounds pretty good to me.
Yeah, good, okay? But, when you explain ... oh, I'm not going to go there. I will go there. I don't care if you don't sleep.
The Mind-Only school says,
Tte husband side of that equation is a video playing inside of your mind.
He don't exist outside of your mind.
So you shouldn't get mad at him. He's a video that you planted in your own mind. Okay?
Got it? I had a profound question for $100 that someone asked me about this.
Hmm? Am I alone is worth $25.
Yeah! When I kiss my husband am I kissing myself? It was a deep philosophical question.
Okay, you got it? Who's keeping track, Allison, can you keep track of money? I'll get ... he gets $75, Peter gets $25.
Okay?
Not euros.
Okay.
Okay, got it?
it's not a bad idea, unless
you say it's all happening inside your head, which they do say and that's why it's a lower emptiness. Got it?
Okay, next one is names. A rose by any other name would smell ...
the same. Okay? Four, worldview number four, emptiness number four, okay?
It doesn't matter because they're both Mind-Only, I reserve the right to confuse them.
Okay?
They're both Mind-Only. Okay? And that is ... it's not true that things are called what they're called self-existently, okay?
Which has big implications.
Okay? Like politicians are always ... some disaster happens and they call it a different name. They put a spin on it.
You know? "It's so good the economy went down this month because it can go up next month more."
You know? And you're like, "Whoa, bu ..."
Okay, you can use names for anything, okay? You can call a fish a rose, it's okay.
Names don't belong to what they're
used for,
which also implies you have the freedom to call the problem with the husband an opportunity for growth?
Okay? And it's true ...
and it helps right? When your husband's yelling at you, you can say, "gee now
the economy is so much lower think how much higher we can get."
You know? "If we start talking to each other civilly,
we've made progress ...
from yesterday."
Got it, okay?
You can make opportunities out of problems. That's the fourth worldview.
According to some schools of ACI.
Number five?
You don't have a thing—you don't have a laptop or a microphone,
until you have an accurate perception of it.
Okay? it's not there.
Everything needs 50/50. 50% there has to be a square here and some metal.
50% Geshe-la has to be not drunk, not crazy, and
between those two things we get a laptop. Okay. Got it?
50% comes from the object,
50% comes from the subject, which is a big difference from the lower schools that say everything comes from the object's side.
The pen comes from the object's side 100%.
So, this worldview number five, It's a pretty big jump. You see?
Half of that pen comes from me.
Got it?
Half of that pen's coming from me. Half of it is coming this way.
Half of it's coming from me. We meet in the middle. That's reality. Got it?
lo nume la nangway wanggi shaktsam mayinpar yul ranggi tunmong
mayinpay
duluk su druppe tongwa
Okay? That's the emptiness.
lo nume la nangway wanggi shaktsam mayinpar.
Not simply established with the help of an unaffected, undrunk, uncrazy state of mind. The object ...
shaktsam mayinpar yul ranggi tunmong mayinpay duluk su druppe tongwa ... is appearing from its own side, but not on 100% on its own power.
Okay? Emptiness ... Lower Middle Way. Got it?
Y'all right? Did I lose you yet? Yeah. I don't care. Okay ...
Highest school. Highest highest highest.
If you don't want your husband to yell in the kitchen ...
stop yelling at your kids.
Okay, it's all coming from that. It is empty of coming from anything else! That's highest ...
emp-ti-ness.
Got it?
It is empty of coming from anybody else except yelling at your kids. And that's the highest
viewpoint. Okay? Now ...
that's the real Geshe method of dividing the four schools.
Got it?
It's not by book, it's not by author,
it's not by historical period ... hysterical period. And it's not by what they think about saving the whole world or not.
Okay? It's by how sophisticated is their presentation of emptiness.
Got it?
So, that's your last homework question. Yes?
Yeah. Lower Middle Way, yeah. Which in the Geshe topics, has a nickname?
Yeah. Perfection of Wisdom. Got it? Did I confuse you guys? Alright .... South Africa.
Yeah.
Somewhere in the history of my teaching career, no doubt I'd said, that but I'm not completely ...
Is is a Mind-Only? Yeah, it is.
Yeah, yeah, that's a good question. Do I have an answer for you?
Hmm, I will adjust what a Pratyeka Buddha focuses on which is ...
Dependent origination. How's that?
Okay? And a
Listener would focus on the Four Truths. How's that? So you got ... the Chandrakirti says ...
the two lead to the ... he bows down to the lower arthats because they are the true source of Buddhas, and
he bows down to ...
he bows down to
Listeners because, listener arhats because they have gained their realization based on the Four Truths, and he bows down to pratyeka buddha
arhats because they are based their realizations on the twelve links of dependent origination, that's the ... that's the main difference.
I'll adjust that, but probably it says that somewhere.
The other thing, okay.
So you're only going to get the homework ...
Jaqueline?
They only get the teacher training homework and they don't get the
ACI, and I'll I'll try to teach what I'm supposed to teach tomorrow.
But now ...
you have an appreciation of
the, of the Geshe course and of ACI—you understand ACI. What we have to do next ...
is go through the 18 courses of the?
Foundation series, and
not the Diamond Way series, and, and we have to look at
what school and
and what flavor of emptiness, and what Geshe topic.
Okay? That's what I want you ... once you know all those things, you can be a real ACI teacher. You can ...
you understand the whole structure of, of the ACI courses. Cool?
Cool ma?
Okay, Fēicháng cool?
Okay. Alright ....
Connie. Miss Connie.
By the way, errr
I don't want ACI to be a Buddhist sect of
any kind,
but I think the prayers are cool.
The pray .. Buddhist prayers are cool because it's a prayer
for the final goal of ACI. We want to take the stars.
sashi pukyi jukshing metok tram,
rirab lingshi nyinde gyenpa di,
sangye shingdu mikte ulwar gyi,
drokun namdak shingla chupar shok.
Idam guru ratna mandalakam niryatayami.
gewa diyi kyewo kun,
sunam yeshe tsok-dzok shing,
sunam yeshe lejung way,
dampa kunyi topar shok.
Cool. By Sunday,  you have to know those two prayers.
In the original pronunciation.
By tomorrow, you got to be able to get your fingers like that.
No, you see you forgot how hard it was the first time. Right?
Okay, thank ... you thank you for being here. Thank you for having the courage to take the ACI teacher training.
We will make you good teachers. You, you hang ...
you stay, you finish, you'll be a kick-ass teacher. Okay?
We ... that's our commitment. Okay?
And and you can help
More people than any other way in your life. Okay, there's no way
to help other people more than this wisdom, okay?
And that's the greatest thing you've done in your life. I can tell you from 66.
It's the best thing I ever did. Okay? You too. Alright. Thank you.